Guide to the James T. Williams Papers, 1836-1947
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James T. Williams papers 1836-1947
Williams, James T., 1881-1969
48 linear feet Extent: 36,000 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01385
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Williams Papers were purchased by Duke University Library in 1970.
Biographical Note
1881, Aug. 10 Born, Lincolnton, N.C.
1897-1898 Attended Furman College in Greenville, S.C.
1898-1900 Attended the University of the South, Sewanee, Tenn.
1901 Received B.A. from Columbia University
1901-1902 Employed at The State newspaper in Columbia, S.C.
1902-1906 Washington correspondent for Associated Press (AP)
1904 AP representative at Democratic and Republican national conventions
1905 AP representative at Portsmouth Peace Conference
1906-1908 Washington correspondent for the Boston Evening Transcript
1907 Elected member of U.S. Naval Institute
1908 Worked for Republican Party and on campaign staff of William Howard Taft
1909 U.S. Civil Service Commissioner. Contracted tuberculosis and admitted to Fort Bayard Army Hospital in New Mexico.
1910-1912 Editor and part owner of the Tucson Citizen newspaper
1912 Delegate-at-large from Arizona at Republican National Convention
1912-1925 Editor of the Boston Evening Transcript, a Republican newspaper
1917 Applied for service in U.S. Army and was rejected because of physical disability
1920 Decorated Knight of the Order of Leopold (Belgium) and Commander of the Order of the Crown (Italy)
1924 Received honorary (D.C.L.) degree from the University of the South; Appointed to Board of Visitors to the U.S. Naval Academy by President Coolidge
1925-1927 Columnist for the Boston American, a Hearst paper
1925-1937 Contributing editor for Hearst's National Syndicate in Washington, D.C.
1928 Received LL.D. from Norwich University
1937-1938 Washington representative for the Chicago Daily News foreign service
1939-1947 Employed at Sperry Gyroscope Corporation for public relations
1967 Returned to Greenville, S.C. to live with sister
1969, Dec. 26 Died in Greenville, S.C.
After 1937 and for the remainder of his career, he lectured across the country and was a free lance writer. Member of Sigma Alpha Epsilon fraternity, Society of the Cincinnati, and Metropolitan, Cosmos, Army and Navy clubs.
Collection Overview
The Williams Papers span the period 1836 to 1947 with the bulk dating from 1904 to 1942. The collection contains the following series: Diaries and Reminiscences; Correspondence; Subject Files; Legal Papers; Financial Papers; Writings and Speeches; Miscellaneous; Clippings; Printed Material; and Pictures. Correspondence comprises the majority of the collection and particularly focuses on Williams's professional career during the period from 1910 to 1925 when he was editor of the Tucson Citizen and the Boston Evening Transcript. While the collection documents aspects of Williams's personal and professional life from his college days through the early 1940s, the last twenty years of his life are not included. There is as well very little information about the Teapot Dome Affair in the correspondence, which occurred during the period covered by the collection.
Williams wrote, spoke, and accumulated material about a variety of topics and concerns which are represented in different parts of the collection. Among the most prominent are Aviation and the Presidential Elections of 1916, 1920, and 1924 which are found in the Correspondence, Subject Files, Writings and Speeches, Clippings, Printed Material and Pictures Series; Military preparedness before the entry of the United States into World War I in the Correspondence, Subject Files, Writings and Speeches, and Pictures Series; Arizona's efforts to achieve statehood in the Correspondence, Legal Papers, and Writings and Speeches Series; Massachusetts politics in the Diaries and Reminiscences, Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, Clippings, and Printed Material Series; and Peace and disarmament in the Correspondence, Subject Files, Clippings and Printed Material Series. Prominent politicians such as Warren G. Harding and Herbert Hoover are represented in the Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, and Clippings Series. The collection would be of interest to researchers studying the League of Nations, the Republican Party during the first quarter of the 20th century, and the political and social climate in Greenville, S.C..
The Correspondence Series illustrates that as a leading spokesman for the Republican Party, Williams corresponded with many public figures concerning the topics above. After moving to Tucson, Williams became involved in Arizona's efforts to become a state. He represented the positions taken by President Taft and expressed these viewpoints in numerous editorials related to political matters. Many letters criticize Woodrow Wilson and Josephus Daniels for their policies relating to military preparedness and foreign relations. Of particular note are Williams's strong opposition to the League of Nations and his correspondence in the collection with leading opponents of the League, including Henry Cabot Lodge (1850-1924), William Edgar Borah, Hiram Warren Johnson, and Frank Bosworth Brandegee.
Also included in the Correspondence Series is extensive family correspondence containing material about the social life and political affairs in Greenville, S.C., where Williams's father was mayor, and about his mother's family, the McBees of Lincolnton, N.C. Numerous letters were written by his uncles, Silas McBee, a noted Episcopal clergyman and editor in New York; William Ephraim Mikell, Dean of the Law School at the University of Pennsylvania; and William Alexander Guerry, an Episcopal bishop in South Carolina. There are also letters from cousins, Mary Vardrine McBee, who founded Ashley Hall, a school for girls in Charleston, South Carolina, and Alexander Guerry, who served in various positions at the University of Chatanooga and at The University of the South. Other correspondents in the series include William Howard Taft, Leonard Wood, Nicholas Murray Butler, Albert J. Beveridge, Calvin Coolidge, Frank H. Hitchcock, Charles Nagel, Theodore Roosevelt, and John Wingate Weeks.
Related collections include the Vardry Alexander McBee Papers at Duke University, the Silas McBee and the McBee Family collections at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the James Thomas Williams (1845-1936) Papers at the University of South Carolina, and an interview with Williams in the Biographical Oral History Collection at Columbia University.
Subject Headings
Aeronautics -- United States; Air mail service -- United States -- Photographs; Tucson Citizen.; Boston Evening Transcript.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1916; Presidents -- United States -- Election 1920; Presidents -- United States -- Election 1924; United States -- Military policy; Arizona -- Politics and government -- To 1950; Massachusetts -- Politics and government 1865-1950; Peace; Disarmament; Republican Party; League of Nations; Greenville (S.C.); Menus; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924; Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940; Johnson, Hiram, 1866-1945; Brandegee, Frank Bosworth, 1864-1924; Guerry, Alexander; Hitchcock, Frank H. (Frank Harris), 1867-1935; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947; Beveridge, Albert Jeremiah, 1862-1947; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933; Nagel, Charles, 1849-1940; Weeks, John W. (John Wingate), 1860-1926
Contents of Collection
- Diaries and Reminiscences Series, 1909-1923
  Several diaries, none kept very consistently, and a few pages of reminiscences chiefly relating to Massachusetts politics and social engagements. One reminiscence (March 26, 1909) concerns a meeting with President Taft when Willliams was asked to become the United States Civil Service Commissioner.
  - Diaries, and Reminiscences, 1909-1923, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1868-1947 and undated (bulk 1910-1925)
  Documents Williams's personal and professional life from college through the 1940s. Contains lengthy correspondence with his parents, siblings, and other relatives. Arranged in chronological order. Also includes two index file boxes numbered 1a and 1b that contain subject entries to the Correspondence. Autograph cards for the most prominent correspondents have been filed into the Manuscript Division's card catalog.
  - 1868-1904, Mar., (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1904, Apr.-1904, Nov., (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1904, Dec.-1905, Aug., (8 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1905, Sept.-1907, July, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1907, Aug.-1909, Mar., (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1909, Apr.-June, (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1909, July-Nov., (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1909, Dec. -1910, Mar., (6 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1910, Apr.-July, (6 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1910, Aug.-Oct., (6 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1910, Nov.-1911, Feb., (6 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1911, Mar.-Aug., (6 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1911, Sept.-Dec., undated, (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1912, Jan.-May 20, (6 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1912, May 21-1912, Dec., undated, (6 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1913, Jan.-Apr., (6 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1913, May-Aug., (6 folders) (Box 17)
  - 1913, Sept.-Nov., (5 folders) (Box 18)
  - 1913, Dec.-1914, Mar., (6 folders) (Box 19)
  - 1914, Apr.-July, (5 folders) (Box 20)
  - 1914, Aug.-Nov., (6 folders) (Box 21)
  - 1914, Dec.-1915, Feb. 14, (5 folders) (Box 22)
  - 1915, Feb.-Apr., (4 folders) (Box 23)
  - 1915, Apr.-Aug. 15, (5 folders) (Box 24)
  - 1915, Aug 16-Nov., (4 folders) (Box 25)
  - 1915, Dec.-1916, Mar., (6 folders) (Box 26)
  - 1916, Apr.-Aug., (5 folders) (Box 27)
  - 1916, Sept.-Dec., undated, (6 folders) (Box 28)
  - 1917, Jan.-Aug., (7 folders) (Box 29)
  - 1917, Sept.-1918, Apr., (6 folders) (Box 30)
  - 1918, May-Oct., (5 folders) (Box 31)
  - 1918, Nov.-1919, Apr. (Box 32)
  - 1919, May-July, (6 folders) (Box 33)
  - 1919, Aug.-Nov., (6 folders) (Box 34)
  - 1919, Dec.-1920, Mar., (6 folders) (Box 35)
  - 1920, Apr.-Aug., (6 folders) (Box 36)
  - 1920, Sept.-1921, Jan., (6 folders) (Box 37)
  - 1921, Feb.-May, (6 folders) (Box 38)
  - 1921, May-Sept. 15, (6 folders) (Box 39)
  - 1921, Sept. 16-1922, Jan. 15 (Box 40)
  - 1922, Jan. 16-1922, Apr. 15 (Box 41)
  - 1922, Apr.16-1922, July (Box 42)
  - 1922, Aug.-Nov. 15, (6 folders) (Box 43)
  - 1922, Nov. 16-1923, Jan., (5 folders) (Box 44)
  - 1923, Feb.-Apr., (6 folders) (Box 45)
  - 1923, May-July 15, (7 folders) (Box 46)
  - 1923, July 16-Oct. 15, (6 folders) (Box 47)
  - 1923, Oct. 16-Dec., undated, (6 folders) (Box 48)
  - 1924, Jan.-May, (6 folders) (Box 49)
  - 1924, June-Sept., (6 folders) (Box 50)
  - 1924, Oct.-1925, Jan. 15, (6 folders) (Box 51)
  - 1925, Jan. 16-Apr. 15, (6 folders) (Box 52)
  - 1925, Apr. 16-Sept., (7 folders) (Box 53)
  - 1925, Oct.-1926, Apr., (7 folders) (Box 54)
  - 1926, May-Dec., (6 folders) (Box 55)
  - 1927-1930, (7 folders) (Box 56)
  - 1931-1938, (7 folders) (Box 57)
  - 1939-1942, July, (6 folders) (Box 58)
  - 1942, Aug.-1947, undated, (7 folders) (Box 59)
  - undated, (3 folders) (Box 60)
- Subject Files Series, 1906-1941 and undated
  Reports, writings, press releases, memoranda, financial papers, and printed materials. Some files may have been used as background material for Williams's newspaper articles. Arranged alphabetically by topic and within each topic chronologically.
  - Aeronautics and Aviation, 1921-1925, (2 folders) (Box 60)
  - Aeronautics and Aviation: (Box 61)
    - undated (Box 61)
    - War Department Report, 1923 (Box 61)
  - American Legion, 1915-1931 (Box 61)
  - Federal Council of Churches, 1919-1928 (Box 61)
  - Labor, 1907-1925 (Box 61)
  - Massachusetts, 1913-1925, undated, (2 folders) (Box 61)
  - Peace and Disarmament, 1919-1920s (Box 61)
  - Politics, 1911-1925, undated (Box 62)
  - Presidential Inaugurations, 1905-1941 (Box 62)
  - Railroads, 1913-1922 (Box 62)
  - U.S. Army, 1906-1925, (2 folders) (Box 62)
  - U.S. Army, undated (Box 62)
  - U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1925 (Box 62)
  - U.S. Department of the Interior, 1925-1926 (Box 62)
  - U.S. Navy, 1913-1925, undated, (5 folders) (Box 63)
  - Washington Conference on the Limitation of Armaments, 1921, Sept.-Nov. (Box 63)
  - Washington Conference on the Limitation of Armaments, 1921, Dec. 1-1923, (5 folders) (Box 64)
  - Williams, James T (1881-1969) and family (Box 64)
  - World War I and Aftermath, 1914-1919, undated (Box 64)
- Legal Papers Series, 1910-1943 and undated
  Several briefs. Relates to the purchase of printing supplies and a publishing company; the relationship between civilian and military law; and the authorization of the construction and leasing of an airplane landing field in Boston, Mass. to the United States government. Also contains a proclamation proclaiming Arizona a state, rent lease agreements, insurance policies, and contracts for Williams to speak at various events. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1910-1943 and undated, (5 folders) (Box 65)
- Financial Papers Series, 1904-1947 and undated
  Chiefly receipts for personal items such as clothing. Also contains a financial statement of the Tucson Printing and Publishing Company for 1911, information about annual dues for different organizations, and income tax returns. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1904-1947, (4 folders) (Box 65)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1889-1940s
  Handwritten and typewritten papers on a variety of topics, including social, political, and business issues. Contains extracts of Herbert Hoover's speeches from the time of his nomination for President in 1928 to 1931. Divided into two sections, one arranged by date, the other by subject and for the most part undated. Also includes fragments. Extracts of Hoover's speeches arranged at the end of the series.
  - Chronological
    - 1889-ca. 1913, (5 folders) (Box 66)
    - 1914-1916, (5 folders) (Box 67)
    - 1917-1920, (5 folders) (Box 68)
    - 1921, Jan.-1922, June, (4 folders) (Box 69)
    - 1922, July-1924, (7 folders) (Box 70)
    - 1925-1929, (7 folders) (Box 71)
    - 1920s (Box 71)
    - 1920s, (3 folders) (Box 72)
    - 1921-1940s, undated, (4 folders) (Box 72)
    - undated, (6 folders) (Box 73)
    - undated, (8 folders) (Box 74)
    - undated (Box 75)
  - Topical
    - Arizona, undated (Box 75)
    - Armament and Warfare, undated (Box 75)
    - Aviation, undated (Box 75)
    - Business and Labor, undated (Box 75)
    - Education, undated, (2 folders) (Box 75)
    - Eulogies and Biographies, 1920s, undated (Box 75)
    - Foreign Relations, undated, (2 folders) (Box 75)
    - Health, undated (Box 76)
    - Immigration, undated (Box 76)
    - Massachusetts, undated (Box 76)
    - Military, undated (Box 76)
    - Press, undated (Box 76)
    - Social Problems, undated (Box 76)
    - Tariffs, undated (Box 76)
    - Transportation and Communication, undated (Box 76)
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1928-1931 (Box 76)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1885-1942 and undated
  Resolutions honoring various people; report cards of siblings; minutes of various associations; reminders about speaking engagements; and sundry notes. Also contains note, address, and datebooks which may have been used to gather information for newspaper articles. Loose pages arranged chronologically followed by the bound material arranged chronologically.
  - 1885-1942, undated (Box 76)
  - Note, Address, and Datebooks, 1888-1915 (Box 76)
  - Note, Address, and Datebooks, 1917-1923 and undated (Box 77)
- Clippings Series, 1912-1945 and undated
  Subdivided into two subseries Scrapbooks and Subjects.
  - Scrapbooks, 1912-1926.
    The majority contain Williams' editorials from the Boston Evening Transcript. One contains clippings relating to Carmi A. Thompson's mission as the personal emissary of Calvin Coolidge to the Philippine Islands to make an economic survey in 1926. Arranged in chronological order.
    - 1912, Jan. 3-1916, Apr. 20 (Box 77)
    - 1916, Apr. 21-1917, Nov. 17 (Box 78)
    - 1917, Nov. 17-1919, Mar. 1 (Box 79)
    - 1919, Mar.-1920, Oct. 29(2 vols.) (Box 80)
    - 1920, Oct. 30-1922, Feb. 6(2 vols.) (Box 81)
    - 1922, Feb. 11-1924, Dec. (Box 82)
    - Philippines, 1926, July-August (Box 82)
  - Subjects, 1909-1926 and undated
    Subdivided into topics. Several were either by or about Williams. Represented in the subject clippings is information about the Carmi Thompson investigation in the Philippines while Williams was in the Philippines working for the Boston American. Also contains information about speeches he made on various topics. Arranged in alphabetical order by topic and chronologically within each topic.
    - Aviation, 1916-1925, undated (Box 83)
    - Coolidge, Calvin, 1920-1926, undated, (2 folders) (Box 83)
    - Harding, Warren G., 1921-1923 (Box 83)
    - Ku Klux Klan, 1923-1925 (Box 83)
    - Landon, Alf M., 1936 (Box 83)
    - League of Nations and World Court, 1919-1925 (Box 83)
    - Massachusetts, 1913-1926 (Box 83)
    - Mitchell, William, 1925, undated (Box 83)
    - Philippine Independence Movement, 1923-1926, undated (Box 83)
    - Presidential Campaigns, 1912-1920, (2 folders) (Box 83)
    - Presidential campaign, 1924, (3 folders) (Box 84)
    - Prohibition, 1921-1926 (Box 84)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1909-1921 (Box 84)
    - Taft, William H., 1910-1921 (Box 84)
    - Williams, James T. (1881-1969), 1909-1941, undated, (2 folders) (Box 84)
    - Williams family, 1921-1945, undated (Box 84)
    - Wilson, Woodrow, 1913-1924, undated (Box 84)
    - Wood, Leonard, 1903-1927 (Box 84)
    - World Disarmament, 1919-1930, undated (Box 84)
- Printed Material Series, 1836-1947 and undated
  [1836 material is located in Box 95 (Oversize)]
  Subdivided into two subseries, one by date, the other by types of printed material in alphabetical order. Includes printed political speeches, sermons, Boston Evening Transcript editorials, political pamphlets, periodical tearsheets, and material about the League of Nations. Contains political postcards, poetry, flyers, hymns, ribbons, campaign buttons, and press buttons for different state and national conventions, including some from the Republican National Convention in 1912. Also various programs and flyers of clubs where Williams spoke.
  - 1892-1915, (6 folders) (Box 85)
  - 1916-1922, (8 folders) (Box 86)
  - 1923-1939, (7 folders) (Box 87)
  - 1940-1947, undated, (4 folders) (Box 88)
  - Church bulletins (Box 88)
  - Invitations and cards (Box 88)
  - Invitations and cards, (3 folders) (Box 89)
  - Membership cards, Passes, etc. (Box 89)
  - Menus, (2 folders) (Box 89)
  - Political campaign memorabilia, (4 folders) (Box 90)
  - Programs (Box 90)
  - Publications:
    - Air Service Newsletter, 1921-1925, July, (2 folders) (Box 90)
    - David Lawrence's Weekly, 1933 (Box 90)
    - National Council for Reduction of Armaments Bulletin, 1922-1923 (Box 90)
- Pictures Series, 1905-1935 and undated
  Includes photographs of early airplanes, including those used in the United States air mail service as well as unidentified pilots in front of airplanes. Also two photographs of persons rehearsing for the Equal Rights Pageant to be given by the National Woman's Party in Colorado Springs on September 23 [year unavailable] which are located in the Pictures: Political, 1905-1924 and undated folder; signed portraits of Leonard Wood, Frank H. Hitchcock, and Charles Nagel; a few photographs of Fort Bayard, N.M., where Williams went to recover from tuberculosis; and several of Williams and members of his family.
  - Agriculture, undated (Box 91)
  - Aviation:
    - Aerial photographs, 1922 and undated (Box 91)
    - Aircraft, undated (Box 91)
  - Aviation: People, 1911-1927 and undated (Box 92)
  - Military (Miscellaneous), 1916-1923 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 92)
  - People:
    - Coolidge, Calvin, 1923 and undated (Box 92)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, undated (Box 92)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1918 and undated (Box 92)
    - Williams, James T., (1845-1936) 1918 and undated (Box 92)
    - Williams, James T., (1881-1969) 1918 and undated (Box 92)
    - Williams Family Groups, 1905 and undated (Box 92)
    - Williams Family Photos--Children, undated (Box 92)
    - Williams, James, Vardry, Silas, and Sumner, 1919 and undated (Box 92)
    - Political figures, 1922 and undated (Box 93)
    - Signed portraits, 1904-1919 and undated (Box 93)
    - Identified, 1923-1930 (Box 93)
    - Unidentified:
      - Men, undated (Box 93)
      - Groups, undated (Box 93)
      - With James T. Williams, undated (Box 93)
      - Women, undated (Box 93)
  - Places:
    - Alaska, 1915 and undated (Box 93)
    - Arizona, undated (Box 93)
    - Fort Bayard, N.M., undated (Box 94)
    - Oxford, England, undated (Box 94)
    - Pacific, 1908-1926 and undated (Box 94)
    - Miscellaneous, 1935 and undated (Box 94)
  - Political, 1905-1924 and undated (Box 94)
  - Rifle Team, undated (Box 94)
  - Miscellaneous, 1920-1922 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 94)
- Oversize Materials
  - Correspondence Series,1918-1940 (Box 95)
  - Subject Files Series, 1925 (Box 95)
  - Legal Papers, 1921-1925 (Box 95)
  - Writings and Speeches, 1925 (Box 95)
  - Writings and Speeches, 1921 (Oversize-box 97)
  - Miscellaneous Series, 1920 (Box 95)
  - Miscellaneous Series, undated (Oversize-box 97)
  - Clippings Series, 1919-1926 (Box 95)
  - Clippings Series, 1908-1930 (Box 96)
  - Clippings Series, 1914-1926 (Oversize-box 97)
  - Printed Material Series, 1836-1923 (Box 95)
  - Printed Material Series, 1903-1947 and undated, (3 folders) (Oversize-box 97)
  - Pictures Series, undated (Box 95)
  - Pictures Series, undated (Oversize-box 97)